okay so the first one I want to look at
this his talk about hierarchy so it's
gonna take me a while to unpack this
because I first want to summarize his
own line of thinking and then talk about
what my issue is with it so the first
chapter of his book is stand up
straightening the shoulders back and
it's a talk about exactly their
hierarchy and he starts with lobsters
and talks about how you know the biggest
strongest lobster gets the best catch
and access to the hottest women and all
of that kind of thing and that the brain
pathway in chemistry responsible for a
lobsters recognition of its position in
the hierarchy is the same as we have in
our own in our own brains in our own
chemistry you think goes on to look at
live all the complexities of hierarchies
and you know goes from lobsters to
wolves and fools to chimpanzees and
talks about how it's not just the
biggest strongest wolf or the biggest
strongest chimpanzee that is leader of
the pack because the Sociology is more
complex and so you know with chimpanzees
in particular the biggest strongest
chimp if he's just the ugly vicious
tyrant world two or three other chimps
will get together and bring him down and
so you know that just being the biggest
and the strongest is not enough yeah
you've got to be big and strong but you
also have to be able to negotiate
relationships within the group in order
to maintain your position anything goes
on to talk about human hierarchies and
that human hierarchies are a whole new
evolution of the concept because within
human society we can create new
hierarchies and so you have hierarchies
of builders you have hierarchies of
musicians you have hierarchies of
accountants and so on and so on and so
on so you have lots and lots of
different hierarchies and in a healthy
society there are sufficient
very hierarchies that everybody can find
a position of some significance in some
hierarchy somewhere or other and and and
therefore fights and meaning and purpose
in their lives he then talks about how
all hierarchies are susceptible to
or tilt towards I think is the phrase
that he uses corruption and tyranny and
that you can recognize corruption and
tyranny taking place in a hierarchy when
people exercise power and influence in
order to ascend the hierarchy rather
then merit that a healthy hierarchy
people ascend the hierarchy because
they're good at doing that thing you
know so is its merit its competence is
the word that he uses which allows a
healthy hierarchy to be ascended and
with all of that I broadly agree I don't
take issue with any of that I think I
thought I think it's a I think it's a
very well laid out schema however where
I do take issue with him is where he
starts to talk about how Western society
is broadly healthy hierarchies because
they are based on competence and he
gives the example of you know how you
don't have bands of tyrannical plumbers
going up and down the street demanding
that you use their services that
plumbers are selected on the basis of
their ability to do the job when you
want it to a sufficiently high level of
competence and again I agree with all of
that where I think he I don't know if he
willfully omits it or simply doesn't
fully appreciate it or maybe simply
disagrees with with what I'm about to
say but the hierarchies in which all
other hierarchies are embedded are those
where the true power resides so we're
talking about finance we're talking
about government and politics we're
talking about corporate influence and
all other hierarchies are embedded
within that particularly the money
hierarchy I mean you you can't really
get anything done in this world without
the use of money in some way or another
and so you know those that control the
the super hierarchies if you like in
which all of the others are embedded are
at a significant advantage and I think
he profound Lee underestimates the
degree to which our super hierarchies
are indeed
corrupt and I give us examples the
revolving door that exists between high
levels of government and Finance I mean
one example that springs to mind is hank
paulson who Yero previously senior
executive at goldman sachs becomes
treasury secretary at the time of the
crash allows lehman brothers to collapse
while at the same time it's you know
insisting that AIG get bailed out
because AIG held huge contracts for
Goldman Sachs which Goldman Sachs were
reliable I think I could be wrong about
this I think the number was seven
billion dollars of payouts AIG would do
to make to Goldman Sachs in insurance
payouts and have they gone under they
wouldn't have been able to do that look
at the Iraq war look at the bonus
painless major bankers after the
financial crash you know the look at the
amount of lobbying that goes on look at
the Buckley and Valeo and Citizens
United decisions which respectively
defined corporations as people and
defined money as speech and so
corporations can now spend as much money
as they want on buy political influence
you know these these hierarchies are
deeply deeply corrupted and I have a
little bit of an issue with his blase
sweeping off as Western society is
broadly functional yeah there's little
bits of corruption here and there but
it's broadly functional I disagree with
that profoundly I think that our super
hierarchies as I refer to them early on
that the real controlling hierarchies
are controlled by a very few people for
their own ends I don't think there can
be any doubt of that in the light of all
the stuff that we've seen since the
advent of the internet and so much Alden
Peterson talks about the correct level
of analysis for getting at the root
causes of the problems of society is the
individual I broadly agree with that
however when there are systemic barriers
to that occurring then those systemic
barriers needs to be examined very
carefully and I think there's a big gap
in the fairness of his expectation where
when you look at the way that
individuals and nations are hamstrung by
some deeply flawed systems that we have
I mean just just one for example our
system of money because 97% of money is
created as debt and debt carries
interest you have this constant constant
ever-increasing shortfall in the money
supply with a greater and greater demand
on the existing supply of money to be
paid out in interest payments so less
and less to actually go around and do
commerce you know that it necessarily
impoverishes increasing that increasing
numbers of people and this is what we
see going on around us and it's all very
well saying that you know lifted this
many people out of starvation this many
children are getting this much more to
eat in blah blah blah but you know this
is not this the idea that things are
broadly getting better this is not most
people's experience certainly not in the
working and middle classes of the
developed world one final thought is is
Jordan Peterson's use of the Pareto
distribution to justify is too strong
but to explain as somewhat inevitable
very large disparities of wealth in
society and again I don't deny the
existence of the freeter distribution my
issue with this line of thinking is that
whatever inequality in resource
distribution might naturally manifest
themselves we have chosen systems which
exacerbate that you know we have we have
a system of money we're essentially
obviously more complex in this but
essentially rich people lend money
supporting because rich people have a
surplus of money
so they've ended the poor people early
interest you pay it back with interest
and so rich people accumulate more money
and poor people get poorer because
things having to pay money to rich
people and yeah sure a few a few poor
people strike it rich and become rich
people but you know for the most part
it's a it's a it's a game where money is
inevitably drawn away from most people
towards a very very few people and you
know I he talks about Maslow's hierarchy
as being flawed because
if you accept the reality of Maslow's
hierarchy then rich people must
necessarily be more moral than poor
people because they've had more of their
needs met and therefore they've ascended
higher up the hierarchy and we all know
from our own daily experience that rich
people are no more moral than poor
people but the fact of the matter is
it's very much easier to think about you
know working on yourself as an
individual if your base needs are met
and while very very large numbers of
people are basically living
hand-to-mouth struggling to survive day
to day they don't have time to think
about them so they don't have time to
think about society at large they don't
have time to educate themselves or
broaden their minds you know what I mean
they're there they're bidding raising
kids on no money so I I think he does a
disservice to reality if you like by by
failing to acknowledge fully the extent
to which people are disempowered by
systemic barriers